former CIA officer, counterterrorism
expert, author, and whistleblower.
You worked for the CIA from 1990 to
2004, notably as the chief of
counterterrorist operations in Pakistan
due to the 9/11 terror attacks. Here,
you refused to participate in the
training of enhanced interrogation
techniques, later identified as a
torture program. In 2009, with an
interview with ABC, you became the first
former government official to confirm
the use of waterboarding against
Al-Qaeda suspects. And in 2012, you were
charged with leaking classified
information to journalists and sentenced
to 30 months in prison. As a result, you
lost friendships, your job, and were
vilified in the mainstream press. Today,
you focus on fighting for human rights
and supporting those that face similar
consequences, and you ultimately believe
there are things we should never do,
even in the name of national security,
and the US government should stop
participating in immoral and unethical
practices. John, welcome to London Real.
Thank you so much for having me. It's a
pleasure. Looking forward to jumping
into it. I think you once said, "I'm a
patriot. I love my country. I want it to
succeed, but I think it's making a lot
of mistakes." And I'd love to get your
opinion on kind of what's happening in
the world. I think I'll start off with a
situation that's close to home over
here, and that's the war in Ukraine. And
I was just wondering, what is your what
is your take on what's happening there?
We're what, 500-some days into it. The
US is pumping tons of money, tons of
weapons into that. We recently saw this
Wagner quote-unquote coup happen. You
know, you work for in the Sputnik radio,
and so maybe you know a few things about
Russia that we don't. What is your take
on the situation as we see it now?
I've got a I've got a take that isn't
terribly popular either at work or
amongst my friends.
My position is, look, if we're going to
be supporters of peace, then we have to
be supporters of peace. I understand why
the Russian
government took the decision to enter
Ukraine. I understand that the United
States was behind a coup, a soft coup,
in 2014. But, if we're going to be
peaceniks, then we have to oppose
war, period. And so, on on the day of
the invasion,
I said on my radio show, which is on
Sputnik radio here in Washington, it's a
Russian government-owned radio network.
I said at the start of the show, I
unequivocally oppose the Russian
invasion of Ukraine, and I urge Russian
troops to leave Ukraine immediately.
With that said, I equally strongly
oppose US and NATO intervention in
Ukraine. We told the the
the Russian government repeatedly,
and I'm talking about
uh President uh
Bill Clinton, President Barack Obama, we
told them repeatedly that we would not
support Ukrainian membership in NATO.
And we never meant that. We we were
lying to them to placate them.
And so, knowing that that was a Russian
red line, we did it anyway.
And we started talking to the Ukrainian
government about entering NATO. We
promised the Russian government that we
would not allow NATO to expand to its
borders. And we did repeatedly, with the
Baltic states, for example, and Poland.
So,
to then point the finger at the Russians
and say this is this is all a result of
Russian hegemony, of Russian
imperialism, is disingenuous.
I think at the very least, everybody
should be sitting at the table, and we
should be trying to negotiate a
settlement to this thing.
Well, why do you think the the Biden
administration has seemed to go kind of
all in on this war? I mean, is it
something as simple as, you know, it's
easy to get reelected in wartime? As a
matter of fact, I think there's almost
like a 100% correlation. Or is it much
deeper? Because they've really grabbed
onto this and you know, if you it it
seems like one of their core platforms
is that we are fighting for whatever
reasons and we're going to take this all
the way. Um not always the party of war
in the past. And just curious Yeah,
curious on why you think they did that
and was it obvious they would do that
from the start?
I think that's a very important
question. And I think the answer
is severalfold. Number one, yes, you're
correct. I think this was a a strategic
re-election move.
Um
Number two, and I don't I don't mean to
sound cynical, but I really believe
this. I think that Joe Biden, like every
other president, uh is constantly
thinking about his legacy. Every
president, for better or worse, wants to
be a wartime president, right? That's
how you enter the history books is as a
wartime president. And uh you know, we
were we were pulling out of Afghanistan
after two decades. We were pulling out
of Iraq after nearly two decades. Uh
what better way to make a name for
yourself for generations to come than to
take on one of the world's greatest
powers in Russia. And to do it for what
you say is is the right reasons. So, I
think that's a part of it as well.
Um and you know, one of the things
that's that's utterly perplexing to me
is what you've just alluded to. And that
is the flip that we've seen in the
Democratic Party. Where the Democratic
Party used to used to lead
demonstrations in the streets in
opposition, for example, to uh the
Vietnam War. It was the Democrats who
came out uh in opposition to the little
tiny mini war that we had in Grenada in
the early uh 1980s. The only opposition
to the first Gulf War was among a
handful of Democratic senators. It was
It was only Democrats that opposed the
second Iraq War.
Well, what what happened? Why are the
Democrats all in? And And they're all in
without giving long-term thought to how
exactly we're going to pay for all this.
And what does victory look like?
Nobody's ever Nobody's ever actually
quantified what that's going to be. What
point do we declare victory and go home?
Is it the utter defeat of the Russian
military? Because that's never going to
happen. The Russian military is 20 times
the size of the Ukrainian military and
it has nuclear weapons.
So, again, what is victory? I think we
should begin to temper our expectations.
And whether we like it at this early
stage or not, get everybody to the
negotiating table.
Yeah, what does victory look like? I
think I was I had Colonel
McGregor on a couple weeks ago. Yeah,
and he brought that He's great. Yeah,
he's fantastic. He brought that same
question up and you know, you've heard
it so many times throughout history. You
ask that question about Vietnam. You ask
that question about Iraq. You ask that
question about Afghanistan. So many
people have openly asked it and yes,
right now, here we are. And you're like,
well, what the hell does victory look
like, you know? I
I bet you couldn't even get an answer
from that out of out of DC. And you've
got the Republican side. People like
Donald Trump, which I guess 10 years ago
you'd think this guy, of course he would
want war, you know, he's saying
>> Mhm. But the crazy thing is both Donald
Trump and RFK, and I you I know you've
had conversations with him and we have
as well. They both [clears throat] said,
I could end this war with a phone call.
And it's over.
>> First of all, do you think that's true,
John? Do you think both of those guys
could end it with a phone call?
That's That's a tough one. Um
Uh perhaps. I I hate to be wishy-washy.
I apologize for that. It's It's
possible. It's First of all, let me say
Doug Doug McGregor is a dear friend of
mine and I have absolutely deep respect
for not just his his knowledge and
understanding of these complex issues,
but for his willingness to go out on a
limb
even when his positions are unpopular.
We need more people like that in
Washington, not fewer. You know, Doug
was supposed to be the US ambassador to
Germany and the Republicans
blocked his nomination. Now, how
ridiculous is that? I don't want to get
too far off topic, but
uh, yeah, I suppose it it it would be
popular if the Russian side were were
able to trust an American leader and I
think that they would trust Donald Trump
and Bob Kennedy on this issue.
I think that could lead to some sort of
a of a settlement. And it's how ironic
is it? How odd is it
that it's the Republicans
who have begun saying, "Look, we can't
afford this over the long term. This is
not a cost that the American taxpayer
should bear. This is not a war that we
need to be involved in. It's a war of
choice."
Why aren't the Democrats saying that?
Why do we have the likes of of
Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez
supporting
supporting appropriations for continued
war or Bernie Sanders or Elizabeth
Warren? I just don't understand the role
reversal that we've seen in this war. It
it it doesn't make any kind of sense to
me.
Yeah, and meanwhile, there's like
hundreds of thousands of Ukrainians
dying.
There's tons of money being pumped in
and I want to ask you about your
theories on the wartime economy cuz it's
it's it it it it bring it comes up here
for sure. And then on top of that, I I
don't know what you see in America, but
here in the UK, you see a massive
mainstream media bias towards Ukraine
being the victor. I mean Oh, it's
ridiculous.
>> And I pull up The Guardian and The Times
and then I look at the New York Times
sometimes occasionally I still do. And I
just look at it and I'm just like, guys,
I mean, if there's any tiny little bit
of victory, they magnify it from the
Ukrainians. And if there's if there's
any tiny slip in the in the Russians,
they magnify it. Luckily, I get to talk
to like guys like Jim Rickards and
Colonel McGregor and they're like, look,
this is not the truth on the ground. And
and if you know that, you look at the
media and even the media can't sell me
on it. So, why do you think that's
happening and what do you see? Do you
see the same thing?
Oh, I absolutely see the same thing. And
the worst offenders are the New York
Times and the Washington Post.
You just can't trust uh coverage in the
New York Times and the Washington Post.
Like you said, they'll take
the smallest setback on the part of the
Russians and blow it up to
you know, the end of the war is at hand.
They'll take the the smallest victory by
the Ukrainians and say that, you know,
this is David and Goliath. I can't tell
you how many times I've seen that
analogy.
Uh in fact,
when the Ukrainians had set out to uh to
begin the counteroffensive, which was
actually several weeks late,
uh it was the Ukrainian military that
predicted that by this point in the
summer,
they would have moved 60 mi inside
Russian territory and they would have
divided the Russian military into two in
Crimea.
In fact, here we are months after the
start of the counteroffensive. They've
moved 5 mi
uh inside Russian territory. They're
nowhere near Crimea and they have not
split the Russian military.
Well, that's
that's a loss.
That's not a victory.
But, what was the banner headline on the
New York Times today? It was an analysis
of how
Vladimir Putin was almost overthrown in
what they're now calling the Wagner
coup.
There was no Wagner coup.
It just never happened. It was it was an
ill-fated march a third of the way to
Moscow
that the Russian government was able to
negotiate out of and the leader of this
coup attempt has been
has been exiled.
So, rather than to focus on made-up
patriotic
falsities,
why don't we tell the truth,
the real truth,
and encourage an end to this conflict?
Why do the major outlets in the American
media have to be cheerleaders for
American government policy? That just
doesn't make any sense to me. It hasn't
been like that in the past,
at least not to this degree.
But, this is what we're up against where
you just can't find reliable news.
Yeah, I've had Seymour Hersh on here who
used to work for the Times and now when
he comes out with his theory on the Nord
Stream bombing, which I might get your
thoughts on, you know, they won't even
talk or print
what he's referring to and they
[clears throat] they make some other
story up. And like, you know, you spent
time a lot of time in the CIA and you
know about psyops and you know about
surveillance. When you look at the New
York Times, like how how do you explain
that to yourself? Like is there someone
at the top that just says, "We take the
the you know, the the left narrative and
we magnify it." It can't be that simple
or do they really believe in what
they're doing? No, it's not that simple.
>> Okay. Uh
yeah, they they do believe
in what they're doing. And you know
what? I'm going to answer your question
with a with a short story.
Uh my last job at CIA headquarters was
as um the executive assistant to the
CIA's Deputy Director for Operations.
Very important job, access to literally
everything. And long hard hours.
So, I had I had hit a lull in my day. My
boss was off in a meeting.
And I kind of kicked back in my chair
like this. And I was looking out into
the hallway.
And I was just relaxing momentarily.
Looking out into the hallway.
And Bob Woodward
walked past my office. Bob Woodward
being the the famed acclaimed Washington
Post senior investigative reporter.
And my brain didn't believe what my eyes
had seen. So, I said to the secretary,
"Hey,
was that Bob Woodward that just walked
past
the office?" And she said, "Yeah."
I said,
"Without a security expert
escort, Bob Woodward is just walking the
halls of CIA headquarters."
And she said, "Oh, you didn't see the
director's email?"
And I said, "No."
She said, "Yeah, uh they gave him free
reign. He's writing a book and and we've
all been ordered to cooperate with him."
>> [snorts]
>> Well, I
I refused.
I mean, like one of the holy of holies
at the CIA is that you never ever talk
to the media for any reason.
Well, I came to learn that of course you
talk to the media when you know the
media are willing to carry your water
for you.
You know exactly who to leak to. And who
you're going to leak to
are Bob Woodward at the Washington Post,
Joby Warrick at the Post, um
uh
David Ignatius at the Post, and a half a
dozen people at the New York Times.
And then there are a couple of other
people, you know, NBC News and the LA
Times and Wolf Blitzer at CNN. Uh
because they're going to report exactly
what you want them to report.
So, it's it's not as clear-cut as as
most Americans believe. I'll give you
another example. I was only on the job
for a couple of weeks. This was in 1990.
And um and I saw Wolf Blitzer
walking the halls with a camera crew, no
less, and no security escort. And he was
doing a stand-up with his microphone
right in front of a sign that said CIA
uh
historical intelligence collection. It
was a an offshoot of the CIA library.
And I remember looking at him and just
shaking my head as I was walking out
like well, somebody ought to be arrested
for this.
Probably Wolf Blitzer and the CIA
security person who's not
escorting him right now. And I I walked
out.
But this kind of thing happens all the
time. You know, they we like to think
that there's this Chinese wall between
um the CIA and especially senior CIA
officers and the American media. And in
fact,
they're in bed together.
Wow. Wow. And it was funny because I I
talked to Seymour about his theory on
the Nord Stream bombing. And then a
couple weeks later I I saw the New York
Times article again with this pretty I
mean, when you hear the details that
Seymour gives you and then you see the
New York Times article, it was this
wacky theory about some Bulgarians that
rented a boat and went down there. And I
was just like, look, I'd never spend any
time at CIA headquarters, but it didn't
take
an expert to realize that story sounded
it sounded like somebody fed it to them
and they just printed it up just to
satisfy some things and just keep it
moving. And it was just had a bunch of
holes in it that even I could see from 1
hour with Seymour. So,
um but I guess the American public
doesn't really know any better. They
read it and keep moving on. And so, this
is a psyops that works. You fool most of
the people most of the the And so, it
proceeds.
One of my closest friends uh uh used to
be a boss of mine when I was on a 2-year
rotation to the State Department. So,
he's a very senior former State
Department official. In fact, I'm going
to have dinner with him tonight. And um
when uh
this explosion took place on the Nord
Stream pipeline, um
I called him and I said, I said, "We We
had to have done this, right? I mean, it
couldn't be anybody else. It had to be
us."
And he said, "No, no, it the Russians
did it."
And I said, "You think the Russians blew
up their own pipeline?
W- What What could they possibly have to
gain by blowing up their own pipeline?"
Well, he said, "It would be embarrassing
for us."
I said, "Don, with all due respect, that
doesn't make any kind of sense at all."
And I talked to Sy Hersh about it. And I
said uh I said, "This was us, right?"
And he said, "Well, it could be us. It
could be the uh
the uh Ukrainians." And I said, "Yeah,
if the Ukrainians had a mini sub that
would allow them to go down there. But
do they even have that kind of
technology? I mean, we're the only ones
that have that kind of technology that I
know of. When I say we, I mean the
United States and NATO."
I just don't get what anybody else on
the other side would have to gain from
something like this. And sure enough, Sy
was mostly right. Uh if it wasn't us, it
was the Ukrainians. We all suspected it.
Uh even though the mainstream media
doesn't want to actually come out and
say it. And let me add something about
Sy Hersh, too. You know, this is a guy
This is a guy who for the last 60 years
has been a one of the most highly
honored, highly awarded uh journalists
uh in in America. The guy was was the
definition
of investigative journalism in the
second half of the 20th century.
And he literally cannot get published
anymore. Uh I'm a member of a group
called Veteran Intelligence
Professionals for Sanity. It's a group
of of retirees from the CIA, the FBI,
NSA, and and the US military. And we
give an award every year called the the
Sam Adams Award for Integrity in
Intelligence. We gave the award to Sy in
2017, and he complained then that he was
under such pressure from the mainstream
media here in the in the United States
that the only place he could get his
pieces published was in the London
Review of Books, which is great. It's
highly respected, but nobody reads the
London Review of Books. They might have
a few thousand subscribers.
Now, here we are 5 years later, and he
can't even get himself published in the
London Review of Books.
And so he's had to take to Substack
to publish himself and to get the truth
out there. That's how bad things have
gotten here in the United States.
Yeah, if there was ever a perfect
example, it's that. I mean, again, look
at what he did with My Lai Massacre. I
mean, this is a guy
>> Exactly. I mean, this is a guy who had
you know,
he's shown that he has a commitment to
like to journalism and to integrity
enough to where, you know, he was hated
and vilified by the military, but he
brings that same ethics to what he's
doing today, and now
that these same publications won't touch
him. And it's like he Sy hasn't changed.
The media has, right? Oh, you're exactly
right. Yeah. The media has changed.
We've changed as Americans.
Like, can you imagine, for example,
the United States ever being able able
to point to someone, some media figure,
and say, "You know what? He's the new
Walter Cronkite."
Walter Cronkite's dead and gone. There
will never be another Walter Cronkite.
There will There will never be another
media figure
that a majority of Americans has respect
for to the point where
every four years people say, "You know
what would be really great is if Walter
Cronkite would run for president." That
will never ever happen again. Never.
Wow, cuz there's nobody with that type
of integrity in that space anymore.
Yeah. That person doesn't exist.
It's It's It's It's a brand new world. I
guess at least we could see it
happening, you know, with people like
Sy, and I know he's had some success on
on Substack, which is great, and I
always love talking to him. He's He's my
only guest that that rocks in a rocking
chair while he talks, and
and it doesn't matter because everyone
watches him. So,
yeah, look, that's great to see. Just to
finish, how do you think this plays out
with Russia? Like, how What do you What
do you think happens, especially if you
take it all the way up to the election?
At the CIA, in our analysis, we used to
use this term all the time, muddling
through.
Um you know, is so many so many people
just naturally their brain defaults to
an either or uh
choice
when they when they try to
prognosticate. And oftentimes, what was
true was that the parties in the
conflict just sort of muddled through,
and things just didn't change over the
medium term. And I think that that's
what we're looking at here. The Russians
aren't going to aren't going to use
nuclear weapons. I don't think they'll
even use tactical nuclear weapons,
because they'll lose the propaganda
advantage of saying, "Look, the only
country in the history of the planet
that's ever used nuclear weapons is the
United States, and they did it twice."
Right? They don't want to be lumped in
with that. They want to be able to
continue to point at the United States
like they've done since 1945.
Um they don't need to use nuclear
weapons, even tactical ones. Uh now they
have a virtually unlimited supply of of
suicide drones that they're getting from
both the Chinese and the Iranians, and
are attempting to purchase from the from
the Indians. And so, what's better than
a small payload on a on a drone that
costs you $14,000
rather than the, you know, 100,000 or
200,000 that American missiles cost. And
you can just lob them into buildings or
into military bases or onto airfields.
I think that they're just going to
continue to do that. I think we'll see a
slight upgrade in the level of uh
of Russian technology that they're able
to either develop or to purchase on the
open market. I think that here in the
United States, we'll continue to arm
and and to train the Ukrainians in
basically whatever they want
up to and including the F-16.
And then, I think as we approach the
American elections,
the Republicans are going to have a real
campaigning issue
uh
going home and saying,
"Why should we be paying for all this?
We have bridges falling into the rivers
below them.
We have international airports that are
international embarrassments for anybody
who's ever traveled around the world. We
have an an interstate highway system
that would take a trillion dollars to
repair.
And we want to move the world's
microchip manufacturing out of
out of Taiwan and Singapore and into
Ohio and
and Arizona.
With what money?
With the money that we're sending to to
Ukraine?
This has to come to a stop.
And God knows already our our NATO
allies
don't want to pay for it. Their their uh
their national debts as a as a function
of GDP are worse than ours.
They want us to pay for it.
And so I think we'll we'll muddle
through the short term and maybe the
medium term and then it's going to
become a political issue here in the
United States where where American
voters just say, "Look, enough. Enough
with this. We don't want to pay for it
anymore. This has to be settled."
And I think eventually it will be. You
know, we a lot of us said this at the
very beginning, too, and I I should
repeat this.
Um
I think in the end
the Russians are going to keep
uh Donetsk and Luhansk.
They're going to keep the Crimea.
There will be a promise that Ukraine
will not join NATO.
But the United States will declare
Ukraine a major non-NATO ally like
Israel or Japan or Bahrain or Saudi
Arabia.
And uh
Ukraine will be fast-tracked for
membership in the European Union. I
think that's how this ends.
Hm.
And do you think this could lose the uh
Biden the re-election? Or do you think
with all the propaganda going on, it
will not be a major enough issue for
people to say enough is enough?
I don't think it'll be enough of an
issue. I think it's going to drag on
longer than that. I think it's going to
drag on through the election. Now, if
Joe Biden were able to run for for
election again in 2028, which of course
he's not even if he were to be alive in
2028.
Um
I think by 2028 everybody's going to be
sick of this. But I think 2024 is
practically upon us. And
you know, look look around. I I'm I'm
looking over for example, uh right now
as we speak McPherson uh not McPherson
Square, but uh but Farragut Square. I'm
one block from the White House and we're
not seeing people in the streets. We're
not seeing people marching with signs
and placards saying, you know, end the
war. We're not. People are just going
about their normal business, like they
generally don't care
because it doesn't affect them directly.
But when we have to
keep raising taxes
uh to pay for these weapon systems, and
all this money goes to US defense
contractors, and they get rich while you
and I get poor,
and we continue to neglect our
infrastructure,
then finally, I think people are going
to get sick of this. Well, let's talk
about that, John, because this is this
is kind of IP that's unique to you,
because I've heard you say the
following, that if we were not
at war or producing weapons for war, we
would immediately go into a recession.
And you've argued that's the case for
the past couple decades.
Um can you explain that position,
because a lot of people would be
surprised to hear that?
Yeah, I've been saying this for a little
while now. In the immediate aftermath of
the 9/11 attacks,
uh we transitioned into what has become
a a permanent wartime economy.
Pre-9/11,
the wealthiest place in America was
Silicon Valley. It had the most
millionaires per capita of anywhere in
the United States. That is no longer
true.
Now, Washington, D.C. is the wealthiest
place in America. And it's because of
the trillions,
with a T, trillions of dollars that we
have spent on the military-industrial
complex.
There are literally thousands of Beltway
Bandits. These are military and
intelligence community contractors that
ring the Capital Beltway that surrounds
uh Washington, D.C. And now there are
more millionaires per capita
in Washington, D.C. than there are
anywhere else in America. It's because
of 9/11, and it's because of our
government's commitment to spend
literally unlimited amounts of money on
what is deemed to be national defense.
Well,
we've gotten so used to, you know,
sucking the the teat, so to speak, of
the American taxpayer
that we now can't shut off that flow of
money to these these beltway bandits,
these defense contractors, without
pushing the country into recession.
That's how much money we're spending.
We can't
we can't move that money. We can't move
those appropriations
to something else
like
uh
transportation, for example,
or infrastructure, or education, or
the environment, including environmental
cleanup. We just can't. They can't
absorb those those gigantic amounts of
money. It took us 20 years to get where
we are with defense. You know, I I'll
add another thing and I I promise not to
throw too many uh
uh
statistics at you, but our defense
budget
is now bigger than the next nine largest
countries combined.
Right? You take China, Germany, the UK,
France, Japan, the next nine largest
countries combined,
and we still spend more.
Why?
To prepare for what?
To give free money to the Ukrainians?
Or
money to uh these countries of the
Sahel? Now, this is all supposed to be a
big secret, but we're pumping billions
of dollars into Niger and Mali and
Burkina Faso and Guinea-Conakry and
Guinea-Bissau. For what reason?
That's a French problem. Why aren't the
French pumping their money into those
countries? Why does it always have to be
us? And why is it a secret?
Don't the American taxpayers have the
right to know
where their money's going and to decide
if that's an appropriate expenditure? I
would say yes.
So, there's no reason for us to be
spending this kind of money. I'll tell
you something else, too. A couple of
weeks ago, a policeman was shot in
Paris.
Shot and severely wounded.
And the gun, the rifle that he was shot
with was uh
was confiscated by the police.
And the serial number on this rifle, was
an assault rifle. The serial number
matched
the serial number
from uh a shipment of assault rifles
that we had sent to Ukraine about 6
months earlier. How in the world
did that assault rifle come into the
possession of a criminal in Paris?
I'll tell you, because it had been sold
on the black market.
So, where's the oversight for these
billions and billions of dollars that
we're turning over to the Ukrainians?
Now, we're not just writing a check and
sending cash. We've learned our lesson
to not do that.
>> Iraq. Iraq, right?
>> did it in Iraq.
>> Right.
So, we're we're we're writing these
checks to the defense contractors. And
the defense contractors then send the
equipment to Ukraine.
Well, the equipment's then for sale on
the black market for pennies on the
dollar.
Why? Why do we permit that? Where is the
congressional oversight?
And even not even congressional
oversight, where are the inspectors
general at DOD and CIA and these other
organizations that are active on the
ground there? This is really a a great,
vast disservice to the American people.
Wow. So, if enough people's paychecks
depend on it, these beltway bandits,
then it's just going to happen. Cuz you
can't shut down all of their livelihood,
so they're going to find a way to make
it happen. It's like a weird kind of a
shadow government, a bit of momentum
there, and they'll use whatever it takes
to get there. And I guess selling more
or selling defense is it maybe an easy
thing to do for humans, cuz you can
introduce fear or uncertainty, and
also I don't know how many guns it takes
to fight that scary thing over there,
right?
>> Yeah. And so, it's a maybe the perfect
business model.
Oh my god, yes. You're exactly right.
It's the perfect business model. And you
look at some of these appropriations
votes, I don't mean to smile. I mean,
I'm smiling I guess ironically. You look
at these appropriations votes, and you
have some of the most conservative
Bible-beating members of Congress
joining hands with the most liberal
Democratic Socialist members of Congress
and voting yes on these budgets, because
they represent this area and the exurbs
of Washington, D.C. And that's what
makes Washington recession-proof.
Right? There will never be a recession
in Washington, because the the business
of Washington is government. But it's
not just government. It's government,
and it's what my former CIA colleague
Ray McGovern calls the Mickey Mac. I I
say the military-industrial complex. He
says the
military-industrial-congressional
I forget whatever else. It's a whole
list of things
complex that makes this city run. It's
it's the lobbyists, and it's the defense
contractors, and it's the consultants,
and it's the lobbyists
in addition to uh
to Congress. And he's absolutely right.
Nobody is going to allow you to take
this away from them, not after 20 years
of getting rich.
It's It's no wonder now that this is one
of the most expensive real estate
markets in America now. You know, we
used to laugh
about markets like San Francisco and
Honolulu and and Manhattan say, "My God,
I I'm glad I don't live there. Who could
afford to live there?" Well, now that's
what our prices are like in real estate.
And it's because there are so many
people who are rich
that they can afford to buy houses at
these inflated prices because they're
the ones making this government money.
Wow.
Wow. And also, I'm guessing if you're a
member of Congress or the Senate, your
local constituency, wherever it is, has
a big chunk of their revenue probably
coming in from some type of defense
contracts. And so, if you want to get
reelected, first of all, you want to be
supported by the lobbyists, and then you
also want to make sure jobs aren't lost.
And so, it just becomes this flywheel
and everybody just lets it go.
Oh, yeah, you've you've hit that nail
right on the head. Uh and that's what
happens even by members of Congress who
vote against these appropriations. Sure,
they'll vote against the appropriation
when they know that their no vote's not
going to kill the bill, right? And then
they'll go back home and say,
"For every dollar
that we send to the federal government
in our taxes, I bring in a dollar 17
in uh in federal aid or in contracting
from these uh these defense
contractors." And people say, "Wow,
that's great. That's what congressional
representation's all about."
It's It's like the perfect
handshake arrangement. Everybody's
happy, everybody makes money, and then
the rest of us, when we realize what's
been happening right under our noses,
and it's too late to do anything about
it.
So, how does this end, John? Or does it?
>> Yeah.
You know, I I'm not sure how it ends
short of the most devastating recession
or depression in American history that
forces us to reassess our priorities.
You know, there is no reason
none whatsoever why our military budget
should be
should be greater than the next nine
largest countries in the world combined.
Why do the Chinese, for example,
go all around the world buying ports and
airports and factories and building
roads in exchange for bonds and
and becoming the go-to superpower in
places like like Africa, for example, or
all across Asia. Why is that? An African
diplomat
told me just recently, he was here with
with his president
for this White House summit. He said,
"You know, the thing about you Americans
is you always offer us democracy and
military aid. And the Chinese offer us
food and new roads.
So, they go with the Chinese.
They don't want democracy. They can't
make democracy function anyway.
And military aid,
we're going to give that to them anyway
because, you know, terrorism. Got to
stop terrorism.
And so, the Chinese go in and say,
"Well, listen, we'll pave that road that
you've been wanting to to build from
your capital city out to the hinterland.
And all we ask in exchange is you give
us the international airport, and then
you give us $5 million that you repay
over 30 years using treasury bonds." And
they say, "Hey, that sounds like a
pretty darn good deal."
And the next thing you know, the Chinese
have bases all over Africa and in
Washington here at the State Department,
they ask themselves, "Well, how did that
happen?
>> [snorts]
>> We didn't see that coming."
Yeah. Yeah, it's
What do they say? You you can catch more
flies with honey than with vinegar,
that's the expression, right? Well,
there's the expression about the two
bulls on the ridge, the papa bull and
the the young bull, and the young bull
says to the papa bull, "Let's run down
and [__] one of those cows." And the
papa bull says, "No, let's walk down and
[__] them all."
And so, it's America America America is
right? So, is that America? America is
this new country, you know, we we we
were aggressors. Maybe America is an
aggressive nation anyways, and so we we
we do business one way, and then the
Chinese are meanwhile thinking maybe a
thousand years out and saying, "Guess
what? We're going to go in, we're going
to give them all everything they want,
and then later maybe they can pay us in
yuan. Later maybe they'll take our 5G
monitoring systems, and then later maybe
they'll join our currency, and they
win."
To continue watching the rest of the
episode for free, visit our website
londonreal.tv or click the link in the
description below.
>> [music]
>> So, Jim Rickards has just recorded a
video that's not available to anyone in
the public, and he's going to be talking
about how this [music] upcoming
recession is going to be fast, it's
going to be bloody, it's going to be
nasty, but at the same time he's going
to show you how you can position
yourself
>> [music]
>> to profit from all of this chaos. Now,
we've made this video only available to
our viewers. Go to londonreal.tv/jim,
[music]
watch that immediately. I can't say
enough good things about Jim Rickards.
He understands [music]
the global economic system better than
any guest I've ever had on London Real.
His predictions [music] are almost
uncannily true, and you can learn how to
profit from his vision, from his
expertise, and his understanding of
[music] economics. So, go to
londonreal.tv/jim or click the link
below. It's an excellent, [music]
excellent look on what's going to happen
in the future and how you can position
yourself to profit from [music] that.
Jim is one of the best in the business,
one of my favorite guests on London
Real, and he's very, very good at
predicting the future and showing us
[music] all to profit from it. So, click
the link, and I hope you enjoy.
Hey, it's Brian Rose, founder of the
DeFi Academy. I've told you my four-week
crypto boot camp is amazing. But, don't
take my word for it. This is what my
students are saying.
>> The DeFi Academy was an amazing
experience for me. [music] It took me
totally out of my comfort zone.
>> In this course, I was challenged, I was
held accountable, [music]
and pushed to do things that, honestly,
weren't always easy.
>> phenomenal, and I can't believe
uh we're already up on our four weeks.
It [music] has flown by. Going through
this DeFi Accelerator, by far,
was one of the best courses [music] I've
taken.
>> You do this course, you really get into
the nitty-gritty of the activities that
will make you comfortable [music] with
decentralized finance. Thank you so much
to Brian and everyone at London Real and
[music] the DeFi Academy for even
putting together an amazing course like
this.
>> Anybody else that wants to do it, please
sign up. It is well worth the money.